<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on blog.janosilles.com</title>
    <link>http://blog.janosilles.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on blog.janosilles.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.janosilles.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rant in the Shell</title>
      <link>http://blog.janosilles.com/2017/03/rant-in-the-shell/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.janosilles.com/2017/03/rant-in-the-shell/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve just came home from watching the new Ghost in the Shell movie. Here is a somewhat spoilery rant I have to get off my chest. Still reading? Good. Gloves off from now on.
This movie is an insult to the original anime. Maybe I will soften up after a few days but right now I have really strong feelings against this film.
Bad adaptation work The 2017 Ghost in the Shell is an average action flick and a really bad adaptation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My command prompt</title>
      <link>http://blog.janosilles.com/2017/01/my-command-prompt/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.janosilles.com/2017/01/my-command-prompt/</guid>
      <description>I really like working in the command line, it just feels right for many tasks. When I first saw a GUI (Windows 98) as a child I could not figure out how to create a new folder so I opened a command prompt and used &amp;ldquo;the DOS window&amp;rdquo; to create the folder. I was 11 years old. Fast forward to today, I almost always have a terminal open and I spent way too much time on fiddling with the prompt I use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code is coming</title>
      <link>http://blog.janosilles.com/2016/11/advent-of-code-is-coming/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.janosilles.com/2016/11/advent-of-code-is-coming/</guid>
      <description>This year&amp;rsquo;s Advent of Code starts in a few hours. I had a really good time participating in it last year. Having a programming puzzle to solve every day as count down to the holidays was surprisingly fun. I had a self imposed challenge of doing at least one commit every day which I then continued to pretty long commit streak right before GitHub removed the counter.
Last year I was using python to solve the puzzles, you can check out my solutions on GitHub.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fun with LVM</title>
      <link>http://blog.janosilles.com/2016/11/fun-with-lvm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.janosilles.com/2016/11/fun-with-lvm/</guid>
      <description>The OOM killer just killed one my tabs in Chrome. As it turned out I underestimated the size of the swap partition during Fedora installation on my work laptop a few years ago. Or maybe I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t just let virtual machines idle in the background and open a gazillion of tabs in the browser at the same time. Anyways, I needed more swap space and thankfully this installation sits on an LVM volume group which allowed me to switch to a swap file, remove the swap partition and add the free space to the root volume.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hugo &amp; git submodules</title>
      <link>http://blog.janosilles.com/2016/10/hugo--git-submodules/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2016 14:13:01 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.janosilles.com/2016/10/hugo--git-submodules/</guid>
      <description>The official Hugo tutorial suggests using git submodules to keep track of your blog on GitHub. This seemed like a good idea but after using this workflow I wonder why is it advertised at all. Every time I commit a change to my theme or publish a new version to GitHub Pages I have to create another commit in the parent repository too. While at first glance it makes sense to couple the blog content, the theme and the public HTML files together on a second thought I do not want to litter the history of the blog source repository with this information.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Faster AUR builds</title>
      <link>http://blog.janosilles.com/2016/08/faster-aur-builds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 15:15:50 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.janosilles.com/2016/08/faster-aur-builds/</guid>
      <description>The process of building a package from AUR, the Arch Linux User Repository, is the following:
 download the PKGBUILD makepkg will download, decompress and compile the source based on the PKGBUILD compress the software into a .tar.xz package pacman will install the package via decompressing its contents into the filesystem  As you can see the last two steps are quite redundant. Compressing the files to then decompress them a few seconds later.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ASUS laptop repair</title>
      <link>http://blog.janosilles.com/2016/05/asus-laptop-repair/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 15:15:50 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.janosilles.com/2016/05/asus-laptop-repair/</guid>
      <description>My sister has an ASUS K43 laptop that started misbehaving. Failing to detect and charge when the power cord was plugged in, making a connection with the plug become fiddly. Warranty long gone, the response in repair shops was the classic &amp;ldquo;we have to change the motherboard&amp;rdquo;. Unsatisfied with that answer I found out that the power socket is a common fault in these ASUS machines and you can order replacement sockets for less than a US dollar on eBay.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>