<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Movies on blog.janosilles.com</title>
    <link>http://blog.janosilles.com/tags/movies/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Movies on blog.janosilles.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.janosilles.com/tags/movies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Rant in the Shell</title>
      <link>http://blog.janosilles.com/2017/03/rant-in-the-shell/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.janosilles.com/2017/03/rant-in-the-shell/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve just came home from watching the new Ghost in the Shell movie. Here is a
somewhat spoilery rant I have to get off my chest. Still reading? Good. Gloves
off from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This movie is an insult to the original anime. Maybe I will soften up after a
few days but right now I have really strong feelings against this film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bad-adaptation-work&#34;&gt;Bad adaptation work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2017 Ghost in the Shell is an average action flick and a really bad
adaptation. Because it takes iconic scenes from the original anime I fear the
movie will be praised for being &amp;ldquo;faithful&amp;rdquo; but I have to tell you, this
faithfulness is only skin deep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The copied scenes are watered down versions of the original, missing key
elements that define the original cast of characters. I felt these reused scenes
were tucked into the movie, lost their meaning, included because they trigger a
reaction from people who seen the original. Take the famous fight scene in the
water for example. In the anime it ends with Batou covering the naked Major with
his jacket. A minor detail which tells us about their characters, both being
superhuman robots which Major embraces, she doesnt feeling naked when not
wearing any clothes yet Batou is not letting go of his humanity and see the
human side of the Major, covering up her naked body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boat scene feels weird too. The Major accuses Batou that he will betray her.
She does not trust him in this version of Ghost in the Shell, yet Batou knows
her hiding place, never explained how or why. There is this strange dissonance,
the film tries to convince you that they share a connection but fails to deliver
why. In the original they are  two robotic soldiers fighting side by side for
years, they grown to trust each other. In the new version Batou is mostly human,
and he only knows the Major for a year, she is basically a new superweapon given
to Section 9 for no obvious reason. The friendship is really underdeveloped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spider tank scene lost all its symbolism, no family tree, no allegories to
evolution, just a dumb fight with the infuriating cliché where the bad guy is
not pulling the trigger point blank but have a monologue instead. The scene
where the Major jumps from the top of the building is in the movie two times. It
is a famous scene, it is recognizable, but this is dumb fanservice, there is no
reason to be there twice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a basset hound in this film. In case you did not know these dogs are
not really part of the Ghost in the Shell universe, they are in the anime
because Mamoru Oshii, the director of the two anime movies, likes to put basset
hounds in every film he makes. There was no reason to include the dogs in this
movie, they tried to use them to developed Batou&amp;rsquo;s character, which is okay, but
it was the only noticeable character development moment in the whole movie. For
me, Batou was the only likeable character in this movie, his character deserved
more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flat characters are a sore point for me. See, the anime is half an hour
shorter than the new movie. It also contains many long, still shots and yet it
gives you more information about the world, and it has better character
development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bad-cinematography&#34;&gt;Bad cinematography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The editing messy is all over this film, after the boat scene batou somehow
disappears when the Major is apprehended in the harbor. Another example is, the
bar fight scene. In the beginning of the scene most of Section 9 is present
together with the Major but after some shaky-cam fight cuts she is somehow
separated for what it feels like almost an hour. She gets captured, interrogated
and rescued while the team is doing&amp;hellip; what exactly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CGI sometimes did not blend in. Cars felt weird, fight scenes felt weird.  I
could not help myself rolling my eyes when Motoko was leaping from one
collapsing concrete structure to another in the final fight scene. This thing
was dumb in The Hobbit when Legolas did it on a collapsing bridge but at least
He was an elf, Motoko is heavy machinery but the CGI made her feel like some
ragdoll jumping around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with all these scenes, which sometimes imitate the original frame for
frame, I feel they did not managed to find a coherent visual language that works
well, I did not get any real impressions about the city or the inhabitants, the
set pieces all felt generic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bad-story&#34;&gt;Bad story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m picking at structural editing errors but the plot is really weak too. The
whole conflict of the movie is that people&amp;rsquo;s brains are put into cybernetic
bodies against their will. They wants us to believe that In the future they did
not find volunteers for this kind of thing while large parts of the populace are
willingly alter their own bodies. No soldiers, no opportunistics mercenaries, no
terminally ill were offered this new experimental procedure which could give
them a new body. No, they had to use rebellious teenagers and memory erasing.
What could possibly go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the motivation of the major? She wants revenge on every terrorist
because they killed her family. She wants revenge on Kuze because he is a
terrorist. Then she wants revenge on her creators because they used her against
her will. An easy to digest revenge plot cliché.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original anime plot is about rogue AI that wants to merge with a human mind
in order to evolve. This may not fit well into the average Hollywood
blockbuster, I agree. But take a look at the plot of another incarnation of the
franchise, the second season of the Ghost in the Shell anime tv series titled
Stand Alone Complex 2nd GIG. The creates of the new movie definitely knew about
it because they cherry picked an important character, Hideo Kuze. The story
revolved around an immigrant crisis in a future Japan where the immigrants are
trying to gain independence while various forces are trying to brand them as
terrorists and gaining political power this way. This is a plot of a TV anime
series from 2002. Given the the current political climate, this plot could have
been adapted into something much more relevant today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The movie closes with the opening song of the original anime. An interesting
choice. It definitely stopped me leaving early, but as I sat there it made me
think of the original and how uninspired this adaptation was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a feeling (hope?) that no one will remember this in a year and I do hope
that Hollywood will not do these kind of adaptations. I much prefer adaptations
where the creators look at the original, understand what made them great and
create something new with those insights. This seems to work with literary
adaptations, I think Arrival and Edge of Tomorrow  did a really job at adopting
their source material.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>