<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>blog.janosilles.com</title>
    <link>http://blog.janosilles.com/tags/soldering/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on blog.janosilles.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.janosilles.com/tags/soldering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>ASUS laptop repair</title>
      <link>http://blog.janosilles.com/2016/05/asus-laptop-repair/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 15:15:50 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.janosilles.com/2016/05/asus-laptop-repair/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My sister has an ASUS K43 laptop that started misbehaving. Failing to detect and
charge when the power cord was plugged in, making a connection with the plug
become fiddly.  Warranty long gone, the response in repair shops was the classic
&amp;ldquo;we have to change the motherboard&amp;rdquo;. Unsatisfied with that answer I found out
that the power socket is a common fault in these ASUS machines and you can order
replacement sockets for less than a US dollar on eBay. I watched three youtube
videos, one about taking the laptop apart and two about desoldering and decided
to take a shot at a repair. I bought some desoldering wick, borrowed a soldering
station and got to it. What can go wrong? If I screw up I can still pay for a
replacement motherboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desoldering a piece from the motherboard took more time than expected. The
solder did not want to stick to the wick at first but adding a little bit of
fresh solder helped. I finished by adding a little solder and then sucking it up
with the wick and managing to remove more than I added. Repeating this procedure
for about an hour I removed the solder from all five legs. Here is the outcome:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;post/2016-05-14-ASUS-repair/before.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;desoldered power jack&#34; title=&#34;Desoldering complete&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this point it was easy, putting the new socket in and soldering it in
place. Maybe not the best looking joints but keep in mind that this was the
second time I held a soldering iron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;post/2016-05-14-ASUS-repair/after.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;soldered new power jack&#34; title=&#34;Soldering complete&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a little anxious after reassembling and turning the laptop on, but the it
worked! The power plug works again, no fiddling required. After closer
inspection of the faulty socket I noticed that one of its legs was broken and
probably could have been reattached with a little bit of solder without
desoldering the whole socket, oh well, next time I will check the legs first.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>